this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at sc-radio.net
SC radio is brought to you by the IEEE
computer Society software Magazine
online at computer.org software
for software engineering radio this is
Robert blumen today I have with me Alex
Hidalgo Alex is a site reliability
Advocate and Noble 9 prior to his
current role he was director of SRE at
Noble 9 and has spent time at
Squarespace and Google Alex is the
author of the book implementing service
level objectives a practical guide to
sli's slos and error budgets published
in 2020 and that will be the subject of
our conversation today Alex welcome to
software engineering radio thanks so
much for having me I'm excited to be
here Alex do you have anything else to
say about your biography that I didn't
already cover
one thing I do like to always talk about
is the fact that I spent most of my 20s
not in the technology industry I didn't
join Google until I was 28 and I spent
most of my 20s working in the service
industry front of house and back in the
house of restaurants so server line cook
bartender I worked in warehouses I
worked at a furniture company and the
reason I like that bring that up is
because as we'll get into service level
objectives are all about providing a
certain level of service for people and
that's exactly what you do in all those
other Industries and I think that's one
of the reasons the whole approach really
kind of stuck with me and one of the
reasons I got so excited about it is
because it really spoke to all of my
experience before I moved in into Tech
cool well we will be talking about
service level objectives before we dive
into that I want to frame this
discussion if an organization is
thinking of adopting the approach that's
outlined in your book so what problem
are they trying to solve when they're
doing that
so service level objectives at their
absolute most basic is the acceptance
that failure occurs right you are never
going to be 100 reliable you're never
going to hit 100 of any kind of Target
something at some point in time is going
to break something at some point in time
is going to change and service level
objectives that they're most basic are
just saying okay we understand this so
instead of trying to aim for Perfection
let us try to aim for the right amounts
right pick a reasonable Target slos are
basically a codified version of don't
let great be the enemy of the good
because if you are attempting to hit 100
anything whether or not be what I Define
reliability as or easier things to think
about like error rates and availability
for your computer services you know if
you're trying to be 100 perfect there
you're just not going to hit it and if
you try to you're going to spend way too
much both in your humans who will get
burnt out as well as literally finances
right the amount of money you have to
spend to make systems done it enough and
highly available enough to even attempt
to hit something like 100 it's just
going to cost you too much money it's
going to cost you too much stress you're
going to burn your employees out so use
an slo-based approach to help you think
about what should we really be aiming
for what do our users actually need from
us and how can we keep them happy the
business happy and our employees happy
if an organization is thinking about
adopting approach outline in your book
how are they probably doing this now
that maybe is not working to where they
need to look at a different way of doing
it so very often there is a push from
the top to be as good as possible and I
don't think there's anything wrong with
potentially striving for excellence
right that's slo-based approaches are
not about being lazy they're not about
you know like losing sight of trying to
be the best you can be but without
explicitly setting targets without
explicitly saying something like we want
to be reliable or let me give you like
an example right you run a retail
website of some sort and users log in
and they add items to a shopping cart
and they are able to check out and
sometimes that's not going to work one
of those steps is going to fail right
maybe user can't log in maybe the
shopping cart microservices is flaky and
they can't get that working right or
sometimes just like you check out and
the vendor you rely upon for your credit
card processing is having a problem and
you know at some point in time that's
going to fail and that's totally fine
humans are actually cool with that as
long as you don't fail too often right
so what you can do is you can use slos
to say something like all right let's
aim to have 99.9 of all of our checkouts
work so only one in a thousand users
will encounter some kind of error
especially with the understanding the
user can then generally just retry and
it'll very often work you know like the
second time around it's about being
realistic about what's actually possible
while also realizing that humans are
actually okay with some amount of
failure they can absorb a certain amount
of failure and you know let that happen
instead of spending too much time and
burning your employees out by trying to
be too good
if I could summarize this then the
approach is about having a realistic and
also rigorous discussion about what is
the level of service that you can and
will provide to your users
keeping in mind the constraints of cost
and people's time and energy yes
absolutely it's about being realistic
it's about aiming for what you actually
need to provide no one actually needs
you to be perfect all the time right
like think about visiting a random
website it could be any website your
news website ESPN to check the sports it
could be Google it could be whatever it
is sometimes it doesn't load and
sometimes that's because your internet
provider is bad or your wireless
connection got flaky but sometimes it's
because that's actually on those
Services right and humans are fine with
that right like literally imagine you
just had that happen to you you would
just click refresh and as long as it
loads again or as long as it loads in
two or three minutes right like maybe
you sometimes have to take a break
you're like okay cool this website isn't
working right now as long as you come
back in a few minutes and it is working
again then you're fine with that you're
not going to abandon that website you're
not going to abandon that service so you
know
figure out exactly how much uh failure
your users your customers can actually
absorb and aim to be at about that level
or a little bit better I guess but
definitely don't try to avoid every
single failure because then you're just
going to burn yourself out I'd like to
go into a bit more detail about how
organizations decide what is that right
level but let's first get some of the
vocabulary down so we can have a more
detailed conversation about it in your
book you talk about the reliability
stack with several levels let's go
through those levels the first one being
service level indicator also SLI
what is that
so the absolute basis of all this is
that you need to have a measurement that
tells you something about what your
users are experiencing I'd like to take
a quick tangent I'm going to say user a
lot and when I say user I don't
necessarily mean a human I don't
necessarily mean a customer I mean
anything that relies on your service
right that could be another service it
could be a team down the hall from you
it could be a vendor right it's just
easier to pick a single term and just
say user over and over again but an SLI
is a metric a bit of telemetry that
tells you whether or not your users are
having a good experience right at some
level an SLI has to be able to at some
point be split into good or bad right at
some level you have to decide this
measurement is telling us things are
okay or this measurement is telling us
things are not okay give me an example
of an SLI that you used in a product or
a project sure you know very basic slis
can just be things like error rates and
and availability levels and latency
right you want your API response to
return within 750 milliseconds or you
know whatever it might be but a good
example of one I actually set up that I
think is a little bit more advanced and
very interesting is uh when I was at
Squarespace I was on the team
responsible for our entire elastic
Source oak stack right so elasticsearch
log stash kibana and eventually we got
to the point where we were able to write
synthetic Logs with a certain you know
ID in them send them through fluent D
into Kafka which we use as an
intermediary then picked off a Kafka by
log stash and then index into
elasticsearch and then we were able to
query kibana to see whether or not that
log arrived and how long it took and
that's a complicated setup but on the
same token all we really had to do was
insert a log on one side and retrieve it
from the other and then we had this
latency measurement the total is how
long it took on average for a log
message to to Traverse the entire
Pipeline and additionally if the log
message never showed up we also had an
availability measurement and now we
needed many other measurements at every
component along that path in order to
tell us exactly where the failure
occurred but that's a good SLI because
it's telling the user Journey one of the
things I always like to talk about when
trying to explain what a good SLI is is
that your business likely already has a
bunch of them to find it's just that
they're in a product manager's document
titled user Journeys or they are on the
business side what they refer to as kpis
or it's what your QA and testing teams
refer to as transactional tests right we
often already have a good idea of what
we need to be measuring for our complex
multi-component services and really the
closer you can get to the user
experience to the user Journey that's
the best SLI that you can possibly
produce now I do want to say it's
totally fine if if you're starting your
journey if or you're measuring is
latency of a single API endpoint error
rate of a single API endpoint there's
nothing wrong with that but you can
progress over time and capture more
components with individual measurements
most systems when you set them up they
give you immediately access to some very
detailed metrics like CPU memory load
average are those good slis
I think those can be important things to
ensure that you're collecting because
you can use that data to help you figure
out whether or not you had a regression
in your code or some other problem in
your infrastructure but an SLI
necessarily is supposed to tell you
about how things look from the outside
and your CPU can be pegged to a hundred
percent for days weeks months of the
year yet the actual output that your
service is providing to people might be
timely it might be correct and so it's
not to say that you shouldn't measure
something like CPU utilization and it
shouldn't and I don't mean to say that
if you are pegged at 100 for days weeks
months at a time that maybe that doesn't
require some kind of Investigation but
that's not an SLI that's a different bit
of telemetry an SLI says are you
operating within the performance
constraints that your users require from
you and you can be doing that even if
you're using more memory than you
thought you could be doing that if your
pods are ooming right as long as enough
other pods in your kubernetes set up
right like however you're running it's
actually maybe okay if you're crash
looping every once in a while as long as
the user experience is fine right so
again not saying you shouldn't
investigate those things at some point
in time but that's not what an SLI is
and that's like captures a user
experience okay I want to move on to the
next level of the reliability stack the
SLO service level objective tell us
about that slos are actually way more
easy to understand than slis right even
though we refer to this as like doing
slos quote unquote right really the slis
are the most important part of the whole
process because if you're not measuring
the right things the rest of it doesn't
matter so as I said earlier in SLI at
some level has to be able to be
Quantified into good or bad right this
measurement we took at this moment in
time or this actual measurement of an
actual user experience if you have good
end-to-end tracing either was good or it
was bad and you can use good and then
total to that's what a percentage is
right you know like you have a subset of
your total in this case good and then
you take that over your total and you
have a percentage now and an SLO is
simply and I try to refer to them as SLO
targets to kind of differentiate from
the overarching term we use to talk
about the whole process the whole
reliability stack all that your SLO
Target is the target percentage for how
often you do want to be good so once
you're able to split your SLI into good
and bad and therefore you're able to
calculate good in total you can say
something like I want 99 of all of my
requests to complete within x amount of
time and then you can use that to figure
out whether or not you're meeting your
SLO our SLO is always a percentage
generally speaking yes an SLO is almost
necessarily a percentage because you
have to at some point figure out how
often you want to be correct I guess you
could say this as four out of five right
I guess you could use some different
language and if that works for you and
that works for the tooling or the
culture you have like that works but you
know four out of five is still eighty
percent right so I think in order to
adopt an a slow base Approach at some
level you do have to kind of acknowledge
that you're aiming for some kind of
Target percentage if if we pick as an
example latency of how long it takes to
add a product to the shopping cart then
would you do a percentage of say the
95th percentile
latency is
120 milliseconds and we wanted it to be
100 or do you say 95 percent of the time
the latency is less than 100
milliseconds and you do it based on how
frequently you are exceeding the
threshold how do you translate something
like a latency into a percentage to make
it an SLO I think a lot of that depends
on what your Telemetry looks like right
like a lot of latency measurements for
example you know by default and
Prometheus if that's what you're using
you're going to end up with a histogram
bucket right and so it's very easy to
pull out you know the 99th or the 95th
you know the percentile and and perhaps
that's your starting point there's not a
ton of difference mathematically talking
about you know aiming for 95 percent 120
second milliseconds or less versus the
95th percentile we want to be 120
milliseconds or less you know a very
high you know percentage of the time a
lot of it just has to do with
understanding what your numbers look
like and how you can interact with them
and how your measurement systems are
able to interact with him but this is a
great point to bring up that you know
percentiles or percentiles can be
misleading so people will have been very
used to graphing percentiles because
they want to ignore the outliers but
slos already give you that so there's
nothing necessarily wrong with saying
you know I we want the 95th percentile
of our shopping cart additions to
complete within 120 milliseconds right
maybe that gives you a strong signal
that does in fact help you understand
what your users are currently
experiencing but if possible sending
your raw data right or your p100 data is
I think a better and clearer way to
adopt an slo-based approach because
you're already kind of handling or
you're able to handle uh if you pick the
right target that kind of long tail that
you're generally trying to ignore by by
using percentiles in the first place so
it's not a wrong approach but I do
encourage people to remember you're
basically applying a percentage twice
which may hide some outliers that
actually are important let's move on to
the third layer of the stack error
budget let's start with the definition
sure so an error budget is basically in
a way the inverse of your SLO Target
right so we'll again stick with a very
simple number let's say you're aiming
for something to be good for your users
99 of the time or you're also kind of
implicitly saying there is that we are
okay with one percent of failure and
that is what your error budget is right
your error budget says everything is
still okay overall as long as we haven't
had a bad experience at least one
percent of the time and so your error
budget is a way for you to understand in
a better way how you've operated over
time right so an SLO you might be able
to say how do we look right now how do
we look right now but an error budget is
generally defined over a window very
often a fairly lengthy window right
something like 28 days or 30 days or
I've seen a lot of teams like to do 14
days to match their Sprint length or you
know but also I've seen error budgets
all the way as large as like a quarter
or a full year even and what what that
idea gives you is you can now say okay
we're aiming to be 99 reliable right in
whatever way we've defined that in our
SLI but how reliable have we been over
the last 30 days and now you can say
something okay we've been 99.5 reliable
over the last 30 days we're doing okay
or you can say oh we've only been 98
reliable over the last 30 days and our
SLO Target is 99 that means we've burnt
through our budget right because that
one percent is your budget and then you
can use that data to have a discussion
right that's really how I like it best
you can use error budgets for amazing
Advanced alerting Techniques and all
sorts of things I really think are much
Superior to your basic threshold
monitoring that that most people do but
really the absolute base is that error
budget status right how much of your
error budget has have you burned gives
you a signal to figure out do we need to
take action right now right how reliable
have we been what does that mean and
does that mean we need to change course
Alex cersney did in the book that I
found quite useful I think we all have a
good idea of what numbers like 99 99.9
percent mean
but you translate that into certain
number of minutes or hours per month I
don't know if you have those numbers
embedded in your memory but I bet you do
for these different numbers of Nines
What does that translate into minutes or
hours of downtime in a month or a week
you're gonna challenge me to make sure I
get this right but you know 99.9 percent
is 43 minutes I believe and you know the
real point is that it adds up very
quickly right like people want to be
four nines reliable which means 99.99
right and that translates to to Mere
minutes you want to be
99.99able the the Holy Grail of five
nines that's four minutes and 32 seconds
a year so now you translate that to what
an on-call shift looks like right like
you translate that and that can be
seconds
no human can possibly actually uh pick
up their pager especially in the middle
of the night and possibly respond to
that and you know fix those problems you
know so yeah I like to translate them
into time not necessarily saying that a
time-based approach is is superior to
just a pure numbers of pure occurrences
right but it's a good way to show people
in my experience often leadership who
often thinks you can attain many more
nines than you actually can here's what
that would look like from some kind of
availability standpoint here's what that
would look like in terms of downtime per
year and when you present the numbers in
that way it can often be eye-opening for
people to realize
yeah okay never mind this doesn't make
sense we can't be five nines we can't
even be four nines the redundancy
required the robustness required the
on-call response required right again
let's never forget about that part the
human element of our social Technical
Systems it's a great way to translate
things so that people really understand
that when they're asking for 99.99 or
even simply 99.9 that they understand
what that actually implies I have been
on caller the company's policy was
outside of business hours if you get
paged you have 20 minutes you're
supposed to be online and looking at it
within 20 minutes
if you really need to minimize your
downtime to less than 43 minutes in a
month then you have to start looking at
having people in different time zones
around the world who are in the office
and at work 24x7 so you don't spend that
20 minutes getting somebody out of bed
and getting them awake yeah exactly like
if you have a 20-minute response time
which I think is for many services
actually pretty reasonable right we want
to keep our humans healthy then you know
you can't hit 99.9 which as you pointed
out is about 40 minutes a month right so
you burnt half your budget just on the
allowed response time so yeah exactly
then you gotta have a follow the sum
rotation you got to have at least two if
not three different Engineers located
all over the world so now this means I
mean a little bit different in the
post-pandemic world the work from home
world but you know before that that
means that you need offices in many
different countries and the complexity
and the finances involved with even just
hitting 99.9 percent is frankly
sometimes absurd right unless you want
to have ridiculous ridiculous response
time you know requirements but yeah
that's another great way of kind they're
looking at these numbers right when you
think about yeah let's stick with 99.9
equals about 40 minutes per month
once you also then add the humans into
that not just what can your computers
give your users but if something's
actually broken what does that mean for
the humans that need to go fix things it
can get absurd very quickly and one of
my big things is that I really try to
help convince people you don't have to
be as reliable as you think you do right
chances are the users of your services
are actually okay with more failure than
you think and find that right target
this is slightly tangential but you know
like some of the best slos I've seen
have been very carefully measured over
months if not years and involve lots of
customer feedback and have been set at
things like 97.2 percent right because
just via actual study that was the right
Target and you know just using tons of
nines I always like to tell people SLO
targets don't have to have just the
number nine there's nine other numbers
you can use there's one other term you
hear a lot in this space which is SLA
which stands for service level agreement
how is that different than an SLO
so slas have been around for a very long
time I've traced their usage back to
telcos in the 60s banks in the 50s even
I found a un document from 1948 so right
after the UN was even formed that used
the term and you know a service level
agreement is well exactly that it is a
promise to someone generally in a
contract that we will perform in a
certain manner a certain amount of the
time and you know eventually this got
adopted by all sorts of computer
services and and computer you know like
service providers and then in the early
2000s HP started to adopt that concept
of an SLO right and what they were
trying to do is they were trying to say
okay we have this SLA a service level
agreement this is something written to a
contract if we don't meet this we owe
someone something either we owe them a
credit or we owe them actual money right
but you exceed you break your SLA and
that means you've broken something in a
contract with another entity an SLO so
it's similar in terms of you measuring
your performance against a Target but
they were invented to be almost like an
early warning system right so you have
an SLA let's move into the future now
right we are a modern vendor we are a
B2B SAS company something like that
right and you've written into your
contract that you know you will be
available 99.5 percent of the time and
this is written into the contract mostly
for lawyers it's mostly there right and
no one actually cares about the money
they don't actually care about the
credit you'll get right that's not what
essels exist for even if their language
is here's some stuff you'll get in case
we don't perform the way we're promising
they're really there for lawyers so
lawyers can say okay we're breaking our
contract now
right that's why they really exist so
slos are similar to slas in the terms
that again they measure your performance
against the target of some sort but I
don't love talking about slaves because
I feel like it's really a different
world slos are operational they're
tactical and they're decision making
tools slas are for contracts and so that
your customers can get out of the
contract if they need to that's frankly
what they actually exist for in in most
2022 applications if I could pinpoint
what I think is distinct about your
approach versus what a lot of companies
are already doing is
the devops people will continue to get
alerted on infrastructure metrics like
CPU or memory because it's not like
those things are no longer important
and as you pointed out the product
managers are tracking these slis and
they have them in their own spreadsheets
or documents what you're talking about
is the migration of these metrics or
concepts that are important to product
into the visibility and actual tracking
of engineering now did I get that right
or is that a correct understanding of
what your your approach is I think it's
partially correct I don't think there's
anything incorrect about what you said
but I do also think that those
operational first level responders can
also use slos to make their life better
right they don't have to get paged on
CPU utilization anymore because they can
instead get paged the user experience is
bad now you may still want to open a
ticket in case your CPU utilization is
too high for too long because it could
still be indicative of something being
broken but you probably shouldn't be
waking someone up at 3am for high memory
if the user experience is still fine
right if all your customers are still
having a great experience or at least a
good enough experience is what I should
really say don't page someone so yeah
again go investigate those kind of
infrastructure metrics if they are
telling you something but you can
probably do that during working hours if
your customers and your users are still
doing okay so yeah I think part of the
approach is to think of the project
manager the product manager level in
terms of our recapturing the user
experience while what are the user
Journeys then again I want to say users
here should include internal users not
just paying customers so I think that's
a big part of the approach but I do
think the infrastructure the platform
level first line responders can also use
an slo-based approach to ensure they're
not getting paid too often they can
investigate that high CPU at their
convenience if everything else is still
operating correct would it be better to
say then that you are trying to aim for
a shared understanding between product
and Engineering about what the business
goals of the system are and get
everybody aligned behind achieving those
business goals that's a big part of it
yes slos you know we can talk about how
they give you better alerting and you
know all that kind of stuff but really
what they are they're a communication
tool they're better data to help you
have better conversations and therefore
hopefully make better decisions right
I've repeated that line I don't know
hundreds of times by now and that's what
they really really give you and because
they allow you to have better
conversations that means it's not just
better conversations within your team
that means it's better conversations
across teams across orgs across business
function realities right it gives you a
better way of saying here is what we
need to be doing as a business and how
can we achieve those goals
to give an example of what might have
been a worse conversation and then what
would the better conversation look like
when they had a good SLO in place yeah
like here's a real life story I've seen
is there was a web application right
like a user facing internet's web app
and a fairly simple setup right
basically traffic came in it was load
balanced across you know a few different
kind of web app front-end situations and
these had to talk to a database and this
database was throwing errors way too
often right we're talking about you know
like 10 to 15 right so only 85 to 90
percent of responses from the database
came back correct and there was no quick
way to fix this because this was you
know like an on-prem vendor binary right
that there wasn't a development team to
jump into the code of the actual
database to fix it and so in the
meantime some of the web app you know
Engineers had implemented very good
retry logic so it turns out that you
know from the user experience it didn't
matter that 10 to 15 of all requests to
the database turned out to be errors but
the database management team did not
understand this right so they thought oh
my God everything's on fire and they set
up an on-call rotation that was two
12-hour shifts a day because they were
only honed in a single geographic
location and they were burning
themselves out trying to do anything
they could to keep this thing up and
minor configuration tweaks and giving it
more memory and giving it more CPU and
all that and unbeknownst to them it
wasn't actually that big of a problem it
needed to be solved one day and everyone
knew that right everyone knew that they
needed to like upgrade versions and I
think get some new hardware I wasn't
actually on the team I was adjacent to
this team you know but you know no one
realized that actually the user Journey
right the people using the web app that
needed calls to the database to succeed
that was totally fine if they had proper
SLO set up that were not just measured
but just coverable and used for
communication okay whether or not it's
your weekly sync or your monthly Opex
review or just simply having a strong
culture of SLO so you can go look at how
things are actually performing that
database team wouldn't have stress
themselves out as much and would have
realized we can wait for the new
hardware to show up we can wait to
install the new version right we can
wait to do the upgrade we don't have to
be so worried because for the users it's
fine because a web app team solved the
problem
story makes me think of another point
that you emphasize in your book which is
that these metrics and our budgets help
the organization Drive how it uses its
resources in this story you told you had
a lot of finite resources going into
people either working very long hours or
being up late at night trying to fix an
issue that had no business value to the
company and yet that time and energy
could have been used to let's say
develop a new product or add new
features and so they weren't making a
good decision about how how to divide up
their labor between Ops and stability
versus new products and features yeah I
don't always love that it was formulated
this way in the first SRE book because
it was only formulated in this way but
the original kind of definition of how
Google style slos were exposed to the
world was basically if you have error
budget ship features if you don't stop
shipping and focus on reliability I
think it's a bit limiting we can get
into all that if you like that's
potentially a very long conversation but
it's not wrong right it is a good way of
having better data to balance what are
you working on what should we work on
next right what do we put into our next
Sprint do we need to assign several
additional people on top of our on-call
in order to ensure we're handling our
operational tasks best or paying down
some tech debt or you know whatever it
might be we can go into so many
different paths here of how you can use
this data but yeah their absolute base
it's work on Project work if you have
error budget remaining stop working on
Project work and go fix things if you've
ran out let's come back to that in a bit
but first I want to talk about how do
you decide if you are or are not over
your error budget is it you've got the
43 minutes and if you step 42 minutes
you're good or is it a little more
complicated than that it's a little more
complicated than that because at the
root of the SLO philosophy is that
nothing's ever perfect and that means
that your measurements and your slos and
the targets you've chosen they're not
going to be perfect either right maybe
you pick the wrong percentage or maybe
your SLI is not actually telling you
what's going on or perhaps you had a
true Black Swan event right maybe you
want to reset your error budget right if
something happened to completely deplete
you but it was because you know every
once while we've won those major
internet backbone outages because you
know but like the L3 outage room few
years ago there was a bad regex that
destroyed a whole bunch of bgp tables
right like you know maybe you don't want
to actually count that against your
error budget even if it burned it you
know so you know like another example is
that same elk stack I was talking about
earlier that I was responsible for at
Squarespace at one point in time we
burnt through all of our error budget
and we knew we couldn't actually fix
things until we got new hardware this is
similar to the database story you know
and this was right after the pandemic
started right so shipping had just
stopped right like the supply chain just
dried up everything was a mess and so
Hardware that we ordered March or April
something like that I was suddenly not
showing up until like August and we knew
we could do very little to raise that
particular you know the error budget we
had and so we could have changed our
Target to something very low or you know
there could have been other approaches
but we chose to just ignore that one
we're like yep we're at like 70 and
that's it and we're not recovering and
that's fine we just ignored that one
until we got the new hardware and we
were able to fix the problems you know
so yeah no like again like you don't
have to be Hardline about it I don't
think it's necessarily a bad idea to
have an error budget policy some kind of
document that says maybe do this in case
you run out of budget but I don't know
it's my favorite term the last few years
it depends right it's better data look
at the data have a conversation figure
out whether or not you actually have to
take action or not don't ever be
Hardline about anything I think be
meaningful in your decisions right think
about what the data is actually telling
you how does that correlate to your
understanding of the world and then use
that to decide what you need to do about
two questions ago you said the the
simple-minded approach is if you've run
out of error budget it you focus on
improving reliability if you have a
budget you focus on features I think
you've refined that a bit and the last
question is there any more Nuance you'd
like to add as to how the organization
responds to the consumption of the error
budget yes I think that part of it is
what I was just kind of saying right
like sometimes just ignore you know the
data right because you understand what
it's telling you but it's not actually
relevant right now and maybe it'll be
relevant later or you know but error
budgets are also for spending is I think
a topic we haven't really talked about
right if you are running too reliably
for too long that can be a problem as
well because let's imagine your users
are totally fine with you running 99
reliable whatever that means right if
you start writing at 100 for too long
right like I say 100 is impossible but
I've also seen Services run for a
quarter two quarters three quarters
right where they really are kind of 100
that'll never last for all time but you
run at above your SLO for too long and
users are going to start expecting you
to continue to run at that level and now
you've painted yourself into a corner
right when entropy occurs when things
return to the mean which they always do
statistically at some point in time now
you're in trouble because now people are
expecting you to be close to 100 when
that was never your aim that's never how
the system was designed right perhaps
that 99 SLO was part of the design doc
right and now you're having problems so
you know you want to spend your error
budget and you can do that in all sorts
of ways it's a great indicator of let's
perform chaos engineering right maybe
you don't want to be performing
experiments that might break your
service if you've exceeded your error
budget but it's a great way to learn
about your service if you have a whole
bunch of it left you know or one of my
favorite stories very few people get to
this but the chubby team at Google
chubby is a distributor lock service
right so basically it's a file system
which every chubby SRE will get mad at
me for hearing but you know it's a tiny
directory structured based service where
you can get little bits of data out
often useful for service startup time
and things like that and Global chubby
which was you know a globally available
version of it was not supposed to be
relied upon but it ran very well right
you were allowed to rely upon the local
chubby right so each Google data center
each Google cell quote-unquote had its
own chubby instance and relying on that
was fine Global chubby was just supposed
to be for convenience you were not
supposed to rely on it in any hard
fashion and Global trouble you ran very
well so often at the end of every
quarter chubby would have error budget
left sometimes all of their error budget
left what they would then do is well
we're just going to shut it off we're
going to turn off chubby for the five
minutes of error budget that we still
have for this quarter you know and even
though they would email right like you
would get an email like as an engineer
at Google saying hey this Thursday at 3
P.M we're gonna shut off chubby and burn
the rest of our error budget because we
don't be more reliable than we're
telling you we're aiming to be and yet
even though this was communicated out
and it was documenting you should not
rely on global chubby every single time
they did this something would break
and that's actually cool right if you
can get to that point that means other
people are now learning how they've
written their service incorrect you know
I know I have so many stories I don't
know how many examples you want me to
give of how you can use your error
budget status Beyond ship features or
don't but there's so much there right
experimentation is a great example just
turn it off so others can learn is a
great example I also love to use it as a
signal of whether or not you should make
a decision right like that one company I
was at there was this failover planned
and failovers at this company running on
pure physical Hardware were very labor
intensive and very difficult and took a
lot of people to do and would often be
planned months ahead of time and it was
like a week ahead of time and the prep
meeting for it was happening and they
were like okay we've spent three months
planning this this is our thing we're
excited we're gonna have the best
failover we've ever had and I walked
into the room and was like hey I don't
want to be a jerk but we're at our error
budget like we have that big incident
last week we can't afford the chance of
doing this right now and everyone in the
room I was kind of a wet blanket because
they were excited for the thing that
they've been planning on for so long but
they realized yeah like that's correct
right so use your error budget to make
decisions at even a very high level like
that you know but yeah that's a whole
separate hour-long conversation we can
have at some point in time yeah I love
those stories and they are great stories
that really illustrate I would have
thought the main issue about being too
far under your error budget is while
you're spending too much on either sres
or you're over engineering your system
but you've added a lot of color to that
understanding with those stories all
right so personally together that I
think we've touched in and around this
but you're having this conversation
about what is your SLO you've decided on
some good slis you've got product
input engineering and it's clear enough
that your SLO could be too low or too
high how do you drive that conversation
about what is the right level that we
want to set this SLO at and how would
you over time get feedback into that to
where maybe you decide to either
increase it or decrease it
this is one of the most difficult Parts
because what you really need is feedback
from your users sometimes that's easy
right sometimes you're running an
infrastructure service and the teams
that actually depend on your service are
literally down the hall or may even sit
next to you and it's very easy for you
to discover if they're having a good
time or a bad time using your service
but sometimes it's teams you know the
removed many organizations away or its
literal customers and perhaps not B2B
SAS vendor customers who can open
tickets right if you're running a b2c
business it's very difficult to go you
know like imagine your Amazon right like
Amazon the retail portion it can be
difficult to go find out you know like
are people happy with us or not but you
can almost always find other metrics you
can almost always find other metrics
that you can correlate against your SLO
performance right so again imagine
you're some kind of retail website or no
like let's switch you're a streaming
service right and you're measuring how
long it takes for your shows or movies
to buffer before they start playing and
you have picked to start off with you
want 99 of all your movies to start
buffering within 10 seconds
and you set that and you realize you're
starting to exceed that a bit more often
than you want to and then your business
side of things realizes our
subscriptions are going down or at least
new user count is decreasing in velocity
if not actually being negative yet you
know you can correlate those things once
you have everyone on board everyone
understands this is how we're not
measuring things you can correlate that
you can say okay when movies take longer
than 10 seconds to buffer and start
streaming too often we're losing
customers or they're shutting off the
movie quicker right if you're able to
measure that so it's all about being
able to take your SLO data and
correlating it with other metrics other
Telemetry that you may have available
very often business based metrics and
figure out okay how do our kpis look
right when are slo's performing in this
manner or not that's kind of advanced
and it takes a while to get there that's
not something you're gonna be able to do
on day one if you're starting with an
SLO based approach this requires buying
and across business product engineering
operations but you can use other signals
to help you figure that out but let's
back up a bit right it doesn't have to
be that complicated it can be as simple
as interviews with people it can be
simple as side note interviews better
than surveys people in surveys will
generally just click great or bad right
like even that one to five slider most
people just pick one or five and go back
and forth and get out but if you can
survey people interview people you know
it's time consuming it's difficult like
I said I think I started this answer off
as saying like this is one of the most
difficult parts of things is finding out
what your users actually feel about you
but that's yeah it's a thing you'll have
to undertake and if you're adopting an
SLO based approach it should hopefully
mean you want to care about your users
more that's what it does right it gives
you better ways of thinking about the
user experience so therefore even though
it's not easy and you're gonna have to
dedicate new time in order to find out
how your users actually feel about
things that's part of the process if you
want to care about your users you have
to talk to them in one way or another
does this suggest thing things like
correlating all the information that a
business has about user Behavior with
these slos for example if a user is
unable to add an item to shopping cart
do they come back later and try again
and purchase the items in the shopping
cart or maybe they abandon the shopping
cart which we don't know for sure but
it's possible they decided to go buy the
products from a competitor yeah that's
exactly the kind of thing you can
attempt to use to correlate I would be
careful unless you have tons and tons of
volume doing that and kind of automated
manner because I think you need a lot of
data to pull appropriate statistical
models that can really tell you whether
or not that's at hand but this goes back
to what I've said several times is there
better data to have better conversations
right you can at least go to the team
that's able to track that kind of thing
and say hey shopping cart checkouts have
been bad what are you seeing in terms of
of whether or not they're returning or
not and you can at least infer right you
can at least make a better decision than
if those two teams were not talking at
all we're getting close to end of time I
think we've hit on most of the main
points that were in your book is there
anything that we haven't covered that
you would like to leave our listeners
with
I think primarily that when people start
thinking about adopting an slo-based
approach they often think of it as a
thing you do right okay now we have slos
cool done that's not what any of this is
about there's a reason I consistently
use the term SLO based approach because
that's what it is it's an approach it's
a philosophy it's a different way of
thinking about your users about your
services and about your measurements and
that means it's a thing you do for all
time
so I see too many people who read about
slos and the shiny SRE books from Google
which I'm not down on by the way like I
helped with them you know you know but
like people read a few chapters in those
books the cool we're gonna do slos now
and they don't take the time to
internalize this is a different way of
thinking it's not just a thing you put
on a checklist and then check off later
Alex this has been a tremendous
conversation thank you so much for
speaking to software engineering radio
we will link to your book in the show
notes are there any other places on the
internet you would like listeners to go
if they want to find you or things
you're involved with yeah you can find
me for now I'm still on Twitter we'll
see but you can find me there at aidogo
SRE so a
h-i-d-a-l-g-o-s-r-e as my handle and go
check out what I'm doing over at Noble
nine we are a company based focused
entirely on slos and helping you do them
better we'll link to your Twitter also
in the show notes thank you so much for
speaking to software engineering radio
thank you so much for having me I had a
great time for software engineering
radio this has been Robert blumen and
thank you for listening
thanks for listening to SC radio an
educational program brought to you by
IEEE software magazine for more about
the podcast including other episodes
visit our website at sc-radio.net
to provide feedback you can comment on
each episode on the website or reach us
on LinkedIn Facebook Twitter or through
our slack Channel at SC radio dot
slack.com you can also email us at team
sc-radio.net
this and all other episodes of SC radio
is licensed under Creative Commons
license 2.5 thanks for listening
[Music]
thank you